Guide to the New-York Historical Society Library Department Records 1815-2018 NYHS-RG 21
New-York Historical Society
- Series III. General Office Files, 1959-2009 (bulk 1980s-2002); 27.17 Linear feet
  - General Files. FY1998 (5 of 20 folders), 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 85, Folder 1-5)
    Includes, among other topics, the microfilming project for the Astor papers, public service statistics, and a survey of reproduction service fees.
  - General Files. FY1999 (23 folders), 1998-1999 (Offsite-box 85, Folder 6-28)
    Includes, among other topics, the results of a survey of library users and the donation of the American Society of Landscape Architects, New York Chapter records.
  - General Files. FY2000 (22 folders), 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 86, Folder 1-22)
    Includes, among other topics, Ebsco subscription service proposal, and acquisition of daguerreotypes from Jerry Spagnoli.
  - General Files. FY2001 (30 of 58 folders), 2000-2001 (Offsite-box 87, Folder 1-30)
    Includes files on, among other topics, Civil War Digitization Project, New York Inside Out exhibition, and a draft of Beyer Blinder Belle's Facilities Program for N-YHS.
  - General Files. FY2001 (28 of 58 folders), 2000-2001 (Offsite-box 88, Folder 1-28)
  - General Files. FY2002 (20 of 57 folders), 2001-2002 (Offsite-box 89, Folder 1-20)
    Includes, among other topics, copies of documents related to a financial legacy from the estate of Ramona Lazare and exhibition files (especially Independence and Its Enemies wall text and checklist).
  - General Files. FY2002 (19 of 57 folders), 2001-2002 (Offsite-box 90, Folder 1-19)
    Includes, among other topics, donation files for FY2002, the original deed of transfer of Landauer collection objects from the library to the museum (though the list of items is not included), and a document considering the impact on the library of the affiliation with New York University.
  - General Files. FY2002 (18 of 57 folders), 2001-2002 (Offsite-box 91, Folder 1-18)
    Includes, among other topics, permissions and the results of a survey to assess the quality of library public service.
  - General Files. Purchases & Invoices (1 of 8 boxes), 1989-1992 (Offsite-box 92, Folder -)
    This set of boxes includes invoices, billings, correspondence, purchase orders, and related documents for the acquisition of books, subscriptions, supplies, office equipment, services, etc. for the library. Principal vendors include Baker & Taylor, Readmore, Ebsco, Blackwell, and RLG. Date range is primarily fiscal years 1991-2001, but there are some earlier files back to 1986.
  - General Files. Purchases & Invoices (2 of 8 boxes), 1986-1995 (Offsite-box 93, Folder -)
    This box holds RLG invoices from 1986-1995 and other invoices for FY 1993.
  - General Files. Purchases & Invoices (3 of 8 boxes), 1994, 1996-1997 (Offsite-box 94, Folder -)
  - General Files. Purchases & Invoices (4 of 8 boxes), 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 95, Folder -)
  - General Files. Purchases & Invoices (5 of 8 boxes), 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 96, Folder -)
  - General Files. Purchases & Invoices (6 of 8 boxes), 2000-2001 (Offsite-box 97, Folder -)
  - General Files. Purchases & Invoices (7 of 8 boxes), 2001-2002 (Offsite-box 105, Folder 1-12)
  - General Files. Purchases & Invoices (8 of 8 boxes), 2001-2002 (Offsite-box 106, Folder 1-7)
  - Calendars, 1990-1993 (Offsite-box 98, Folder -)
    Includes what appears to be the master calendars for the library staff, 1990-93, and the daily calendar for the administrative assistant (1992).
  - Grants (1 of 4 boxes), 1982-1992 (Offsite-box 99, Folder 1-12)
    Includes Annie Laurie Aitken Charitable Trust (library preservation, book conservation), Vincent Astor Foundation, U.S. Dept. of Education (Rufus King Collection), Gladys Brook Foundation, Library of Congress, and NEH (renovations & rehousing).
  - Grants (2 of 4 boxes), 1992-1999 (Offsite-box 100, Folder 1-16)
    Includes NEH Map project.
  - Grants (3 of 4 boxes), 1990-1993 (Offsite-box 101, Folder 1-7)
    Includes NEH Regional Americana Project (RAP), NHPRC (general information), and Pew Charitable Trust (library cataloging).
  - Grants (4 of 4 boxes), 1986-1999 (Offsite-box 102, Folder 1-12)
    Includes New York State grants (Erskine-Dewitt maps, manuscript survey, conservation).
  - Fellowship Proposals (29 folders), 2002-2003 (Offsite-box 103, Folder 1-29)
  - Friends of the Library (22 folders), 1988-1989 (Offsite-box 104, Folder 1-22)
  - Library Statistics (6 folders), 1981-1991 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 1-6)
  - Long Range Planning Project, 1986 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports (4 folders), 1980-1992 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 8-11)
    Includes the Library annual report for 1980-82 and 1992, Reading Room for 1986, and Technical Services for 1987.
  - Acquisition Policy Amendments, 1959-1975 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 12)
    Includes two bound copies of the 1959 policy annotated with the 1971 amendments. One copy also has loose sheets that include an outline of trustee John Parsons's proposed changes to Jim Heslin and the proposed revisions circulated to the Library Committee in 1971. Also includes a copy of the 1975 statement.
  - Acquisitions [Accessioning] Procedures, 1985 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 12)
  - Cataloging Projects. Memos (9 folders), 1974-1987 (Offsite-box 154, Folder 1-9)
  - Cataloging. Statistics (3 folders), 1984-1989 (Offsite-box 154, Folder 10-12)
  - Staff Guidelines, Manuscript Department, 2002-2004 (Offsite-box 108, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Processing Procedures, 1982-1993 (Offsite-box 108, Folder 2)
  - Library Forms, Undated (Offsite-box 108, Folder 3)
  - Library Documents (from binder) (3 folders), circa 1992 (Offsite-box 108, Folder 4-6)
  - Library Documents (from binder) (3 folders), circa 1992 (Offsite-box 109, Folder 2-4)
  - Library Documents (from binder) (2 folders), circa 1992-1993 (Offsite-box 109, Folder 5-6)
  - Disaster Recovery and Emergency Plans (3 of 4 folders), 1989-2009 (Offsite-box 108, Folder 7-9)
  - Disaster Recovery and Emergency Plans (1 of 4 folders), 1989 (Offsite-box 109, Folder 1)
    Includes a second copy of the library's disaster recovery plan found above.
  - Library Staff Party and Event Announcements, 1985-1991 (Offsite-box 109, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Memos (9 folders), 1982-1992 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 1-9)
  - Budgets (6 folders), 1961-1988 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 10-15)
    Includes some workpapers for budgets from 1961-early 1980s with fuller budget documents for fiscal years 1985-88.
  - IRLA and RLG correspondence and reports (8 folders), 1981-1993 (Offsite-box 359)
- Series IV. Librarian & Curatorial Files, 1959-2013; 31.21 Linear feet
  The series includes files that can be attributed, at least in large part, to particular individuals who headed the Library and/or played manuscript curatorial roles. These include Librarians (i.e., head of the Library) James Gregory (1966-1980), Larry Sullivan (1980-1984), Paul Cohen (1984-1987), James Mooney (1987-1989), Jean Ashton (1990-1993), Margaret Heilbrun (1993-2003), and, returning to N-YHS from Columbia University, Jean Ashton (2006-2012). Also included are files from manuscript curators Arthur Breton (1960s), Thomas Dunnings (1970s-1980s and institutional archivist, 1990-1993), Margaret Heilbrun (1987-1993), and Donna Davey (circa 2001-2004).
  The series includes a broad range of subject matter, including budgets, management reports, statistics, library policies, exhibition planning, grants and projects (e.g., microfilming, cataloging, institutional archive, digitization), acquisitions and sales through Swann Galleries and other dealers, donations, collection surveys and consultant reports, general correspondence including inquiries and permissions, conservation, research fellowships, and more. The container list below includes further content description at the box level.
  The series is arranged by individual principally associated with a set of files, in rough chronological order.
  Reflecting her two separate tenures at N-YHS, Jean Ashton's files are in two sets, designated in the container list as Jean Ashton I (1985-1993) and Jean Ashton II (2003-2013).
  Margaret Heilbrun's files are presented in four sets that reflect the state of the records as found by the processing archivist in 2016. There is significant overlap in the content and date range of the sets. Set 1 includes relatively well-structured subject files in alphabetical order that date primarily, though not exclusively, from Heilbrun's tenure as head of the Library. Set 2 includes a less structured mix of subject matter that date primarily, though not exclusively from Heilbrun's years as curator of manuscripts prior to leading the Library. Set 3 includes records from her last two years at N-YHS. Set 4 includes various materials associated with Heilbrun and Heilbrun's years in the Library that were compiled from loose and unorganized documents by the processing archivist in 2016.
  - Arthur Breton Files (3 folders), 1962-1972 (Offsite-box 110, Folder 1-3)
    Includes correspondence including that concerning Breton's manuscript guide.
  - Thomas Dunnings Files (1 of 4 boxes), 1963-1992 (Offsite-box 111, Folder 1-28)
    Includes, among other topics, exhibition (manuscripts on display, FDR, Washington, Great Fire, and Constitution), papers location guide, and AMC logs. There is also a set of folders containing a report by Richard B. Morris and the Mayor's Task Force on the New York City Municipal Archives (1966) (Heslin was a member of the Task Force) and Frank G. Burke's report on selected archival problems in New York's records.
  - Thomas Dunnings Files (2 of 4 boxes), 1959-1991 (Offsite-box 112, Folder 1-9)
    Includes, among other topics, memos, inventories and other documents related to Dunnings's development of the institutional archive.
  - Thomas Dunnings Files (3 of 4 boxes), 1971-1993 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 1-13)
  - Thomas Dunnings Files (4 of 4 boxes), 1970-1992 (Offsite-box 114, Folder 1-8)
    Includes general correspondence of the Manuscripts Department, principally reference-related.
  - James Gregory Files (1 of 3 boxes), 1967-1983 (Offsite-box 115, Folder 1-11)
    Includes the general correspondence files A-Z and subject files A-C, including Burleigh's Views of New York, Aaron Burr papers microfilm project, and Christie's (including sale of N-YHS's S.V. Hoffman items in 1975).
  - James Gregory Files (2 of 3 boxes), 1970-1984, 1988 (Offsite-box 116, Folder 1-12)
    Includes, among others, subject files D-P, including Gates paper microfilm project, sale of S.V. Hoffman books, the LeBoeuf Fulton collection, an auction catalogue for Gregory's personal library (1988), Microfilming Corp of America (MCA), Old Print Shop, Papprill's View of New York, and trustees Andrew Oliver and John E. Parsons.
  - James Gregory Files (3 of 3 boxes), 1961-1983 (Offsite-box 117, Folder 1-8)
    Includes subject files R-W, including donations from A. Pennington Whitehead, N-YHS sales at Swann Galleries, the 1969 list of Treasures of Americana, and correspondence with trustees Frank Streeter, Thomas Streeter, and Alexander Vietor.
  - Larry Sullivan Files (1 of 3 boxes), 1976-1984 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 1-13)
    Includes general correspondence files A-Z and subject files that include, among other topics, loans to the American Antiquarian Society for their early American imprints project, NYU paper conservator Konstanze Bachmann's report on N-YHS's architectural collections, and dealings with bookseller Roger Butterfield.
  - Larry Sullivan Files (2 of 3 boxes), 1977-1990 (Offsite-box 119, Folder 1-21)
    Includes subject files D-T including, among other topics, deaccessions, statements of work goals made by individual library staff members, a report by John F. Dean of Johns Hopkins on N-YHS's collections care/conservation, dealings with the Old Print Shop (a ledger in the file also includes records related to dealings with Roger Butterfield; some documents in this file extend to 1990) and Swann Galleries.
  - Larry Sullivan Files (3 of 3 boxes), 1979-1984 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 1-12)
    Includes correspondence concerning research requests and other forms of library resource-related assistance.
  - Paul Cohen Files (8 folders), 1984-1987 (Offsite-box 121, Folder 1-8)
    Includes general correspondence files A-Z, the final report to the NEH on N-YHS's grant-funded participation in RLG (1982-86), a summary of a meeting at N-YHS of the Mid-Atlantic Cooperative Preservation Service Facility (MASCPS, of which N-YHS was a member) and a related microfilming grant proposal, loan of objects for the U.S. Grant centennial exhibition, and a grant proposal for cataloging the Rufus King collection.
  - James Mooney Files (1 of 4 boxes), 1986-1991 (Offsite-box 122, Folder 1-17)
    Includes general correspondence files A-Z, primarily for 1987. Also includes files of correspondence with specific individuals, principally consultants concerning various aspects of the library collection.
  - James Mooney Files (2 of 4 boxes), 1984-1989 (Offsite-box 123, Folder 1-15)
    Includes weekly calendars, monthly reports from the library to Director James Bell, and files of offsite storage and general conservation matters.
  - James Mooney Files (3 of 4 boxes), 1985-1989 (Offsite-box 124, Folder 1-19)
    Includes subject files including, among others, the Summer Institute for history teachers, Long Island fishing documentary project, US-China trade film, the exhibition at the Nippon Club, playing card collection, planning, Print Room (Zinkham guide), and the Encyclopedia of New York City.
  - James Mooney Files (4 of 4 boxes), 1986-1988 (Offsite-box 133, Folder 1-16)
    Includes exhibition files, primarily Government by Choice: Inventing the U.S. Constitution, but also Strong on Music, New York Bestiary, Putting New York on the Map, and Ex Libris Rufus King.
  - Jean Ashton I Files (Box 1 of 6), 1987-1993 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 1-17)
    Includes subject files A-E including, among other topics, advisory committees, library annual reports, conservation procedures, general correspondence (1993), development, and education programs.
  - Jean Ashton I Files (Box 2 of 6), 1989-1992 (Offsite-box 127, Folder 1-28)
    Includes subject files related to proposed or installed exhibitions including Library Treasures, Letters from a War, "Patronage," "Tokyo Map Show," "Bicentennial of the US Constitution," "Thomas Jefferson," and Markers of Change.
  - Jean Ashton I Files (Box 3 of 6), 1985-1993 (Offsite-box 128, Folder 1-18)
    Includes subject files F, primarily including correspondence related to the fiscal crisis.
  - Jean Ashton I Files (Box 4 of 6), 1985-1993 (Offsite-box 129, Folder 1-17)
    Includes subject files G-N including, among other topics, grants, Jewish Museum, lecture series, general manuscript matters, memo files, microfilming, and newspapers.
  - Jean Ashton I Files (Box 5 of 6), 1987-1993 (Offsite-box 130, Folder 1-15)
    Includes subject files O-P, including among other topics, organizational charts, permissions, planning (including collection management policies), preservation, public service, and publications.
  - Jean Ashton I Files (Box 6 of 6), 1990-1993 (Offsite-box 131, Folder 1-23)
    Includes subject files R-V, including among other topics, the Gallery Reinstallation Committee, RLG, RECON project, series and standing orders cancelled, library de-selections, stacks planning, Technical Services, and Ashton's testimony at a public hearing on the preservation of historical records (1990).
  - Jean Ashton I Files (Box 1 of 2), 1980s-1992 (Offsite-box 356)
    This and the following box were found after processing was completed on the record group and was added here. The files are not processed and are in original folders. The content includes a broad range of library adminstration matters.
  - Jean Ashton I Files (Box 2 of 2) (Offsite-box 357)
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 1 (1 of 8 boxes), 1993-2001 (Offsite-box 134, Folder 1-47)
    Includes subject files A-C, including among other topics, acquisitions, access policies, library annual reports, Beekman Family Association, capital funding, and Collections Advisory Committee.
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 1 (2 of 8 boxes), 1984-1998 (Offsite-box 135, Folder 1-48)
    Includes subject files C-G, including among other topics, collections management, general correspondence (1993-94), Friends of the Library, and grants and grants proposed (Cass Gilbert, negatives, maps, Mellon).
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 1 (3 of 8 boxes), 1992-1999 (Offsite-box 136, Folder 1-57)
    Includes subject files G-L, including among other topics, various grant projects, correspondence with former mayor Edward Koch about a possible donation of materials, an original receipt acknowledgement from the Holland Society of a returned deposit, various library administrative matters (e.g., budget, fees, staffing, stacks, etc.), and Luce Center.
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 1 (4 of 8 boxes), 1989-1997 (Offsite-box 137, Folder 1-56)
    Includes subject files M, including manuscript department matters (collection descriptions, cataloguing, etc.) and microfilming (Archives Preservation Microfilming Project/RLG).
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 1 (5 of 8 boxes), 1990-2003 (Offsite-box 138, Folder 1-17)
    This box and the next includes subject files for the Mellon grant-funded project to catalog N-YHS collections in partnership with New York University as well as general N-YHS-NYU subject files.
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 1 (6 of 8 boxes), 1990-2003 (Offsite-box 139, Folder 1-19)
    Includes the continuation of the Mellon-related files.
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 1 (7 of 8 boxes), 1990-2002 (Offsite-box 140, Folder 1-71)
    Includes subject files N-S, including among other topics, planning, public service, Rockefeller Foundation proposal, and bequest of the estate of Steutel-Dean..
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 1 (8 of 8 boxes), 1991-1998 (Offsite-box 141, Folder 1-20)
    Includes subject files T-Z.
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 2 (1 of 4 boxes), 1988-2000 (Offsite-box 143, Folder 1-32)
    Includes a mix of subjects, including among others, acquisition notes, collection development, planning, and development.
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 2 (2 of 4 boxes), 1981-2001 (Offsite-box 144, Folder 1-30)
    Includes a mix of subjects, including among others, space allocation, technical services (Innopac, RLIN, microfilming, conservation, etc.), manuscript department matters, public service (including statistics), and public programs.
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 2 (3 of 4 boxes), 1989-1998 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 1-9)
    Includes a mix of subjects including small work files for a few exhibitions and records of temporary removals/loans from the collection.
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 2 (4 of 4 boxes), 1989-1998 (Offsite-box 146, Folder 1-7)
    Includes a mix of subjects including records of temporary removals/loans from the collection and general correspondence (1989-1993).
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 3 (1 of 2 boxes), 2001-2003 (Offsite-box 147, Folder 1-41)
    Includes memos, permissions, general correspondence, donation files, fellowships, statistics, and some subject files.
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 3 (2 of 2 boxes), 2001-2003 (Offsite-box 148, Folder 1-31)
    Includes grants, memos, and some subject files.
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 4 (1 of 3 boxes), 1989-2003 (Offsite-box 149, Folder 1-55)
    Includes a compiled mix of files generally concerning acquisitions, collection surveys and descriptions, a few small exhibition files, a library procedures manual (circa 2000), public service and other statistics, the World Trade Center/9-11/History Responds project, N-YHS web site, and other matter.
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 4 (2 of 3 boxes), 1983-2003 (Offsite-box 150, Folder 1-48)
    Includes a compiled mix of files generally concerning grants (including actual and potential Mellon projects), budgets, some bills and invoices, goals, planning, consultants, conservation, space planning, "Resources in New York City History" project, Bobcat (library catalog) search procedures, and a cataloging department quick reference notebook.
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Set 4 (3 of 3 boxes), 1994-2003 (Offsite-box 151, Folder 1-6)
    Includes a compiled mix of general correspondence, memos and printed emails.
  - Margaret Heilbrun Files. Phone Messages and Desk Calendars, 1993-2000, 2003 (Offsite-box 152, Item 1-12)
  - Mellon Digital Project. "Civil War Treasures at N-YHS", 1998-2000 (Offsite-box 153, Folder 1-16)
  - Donna Davey Files (1 of 3 boxes), 2001-2004 (Offsite-box 155, Folder 1-49)
    Includes subject files A-S (end), including among other topics, budgets, grants (including Delmas for organizing the institutional archive and Mellon), small files on some exhibitions, and statistics and library survey sheets.
  - Donna Davey Files (2 of 3 boxes), 2001-2004 (Offsite-box 156, Folder 1-12)
    Includes notes, research, and photocopies of documents related to the library's revolving exhibition of presidential letters.
  - Donna Davey Files (3 of 3 boxes), 2002-2004 (Offsite-box 157, Folder 1-14)
    Includes the drafts and finals of the various consultant reports on the Mellon-funded Contemporary Collecting policy project. Also includes general administrative files on meetings and correspondence.
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 1 (1 of 3 boxes), 2006-2008 (Offsite-box 158, Folder 1-16)
    Includes subject files A-B, including among other topics, "About the Library" fact sheet, African-American History Trust booklet, African Free School presentation book, conservation of Arthur Curtiss James scrapbook, final report for the Brown Brothers Harriman project, and buildings and stacks plans.
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 1 (2 of 3 boxes), 2006-2010? (Offsite-box 159, Folder 1-21)
    Includes subject files B-L, including among other topics, buildings/space planning, Chairman's Council "Weekend with History" packet (2007), proposed exhibition re: Winston Churchill, general exhibition information, library collection policies, collections reviews (e.g. for duplicate holdings), Friends of the Library, N-YHS's Graduate Institute in American History, and library administration (statistics, lists of tours, priorities, staffing, etc.)
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 1 (3 of 3 boxes), 2006-2009 (Offsite-box 160, Folder 1-25)
    Includes subject files L-Y, including among other topics, Library Night, nitrate film project report, Questions about New York Author Guide & Checklist, New York Genealogical & Biographical Society Library proposal, N-YHS records from Bobcat database, stacks planning, diaries of Gouverneur Morris project, project proposals, general Print Room matters, rare book collection project, records management proposals, electronic reference database assessment, renovation planning, John Rink's plan of Central Park, proposal to Russell Sage, and Shattuck exhibition proposal.
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 2 (1 of 11 boxes), 2005-2013 (Offsite-box 161, Folder 1-26)
    Includes files of deeds of gifts for FY 2006-FY2013 and acknowledgement letters for FY2006-FY2010.
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 2 (2 of 11 boxes), 2007-2013 (Offsite-box 162, Folder 1-40)
    Includes acknowledgement letters for FY2011-FY2013, files on individual donations or potential donations (including Causeries du Lundi, Central Park Conservancy, Children's Aid Society, New York Foundling, among others), and routing slips with acquisition data.
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 2 (3 of 11 boxes), 2006-2012 (Offsite-box 163, Folder 1-31)
    Includes files on purchases, deaccessioning policies, permission requests, and finding aids/inventories for various collections.